Okay, I'm excited to introduce our next speaker. Show of
---
好的，我很兴奋地介绍下一位演讲者。来，举手看看，
hands, who here uses Claude code?
---
这里谁在用Claude代码？
Okay, show of hands, who here has code psychosis?
---
行，举手看看，谁有代码狂热症？
Come on guys, [clears throat] it's okay.
---
来吧朋友们，[清嗓子] 这没什么大不了的。
Come on guys, [clears throat] it's okay. It's Um my
---
来吧朋友们，[清嗓子] 这没什么大不了的。
team lovingly says I have Claude code psychosis, which
---
嗯……我的团队开玩笑说我有代码狂热症，
may or not be true. we
---
这可能是真的也可能不是。
are delighted to Boris Cherny with us today. Uh is the creator,
---
今天我们有幸请到了Boris Cherny。呃，
father of code. and uh in process doing that has just
---
他是代码的创造者、奠基人。在这个过程中，
had a front row seat reinventing modern way software development.
---
他亲眼见证了现代软件开发方式的革新。
modern way of software development. Um and we're really grateful to
---
现代软件开发方式。嗯，我们真的很感激您Boris，
you, Boris, for taking the time
---
今天能抽出时间与我们交流。
speak with us today. We know that um entirety development kind rests on
---
我们知道整个开发领域的发展某种程度上都扛在您肩上。所以，
your shoulders.
---
感谢您前来。
So, thank it out be And interviewing is Lauren Reader from our team.
---
今天采访您的是我们团队的Lauren Reader。
Um you took my opening line, Asia.
---
嗯，Aisa你抢了我的开场白。
We asked who here uses Claude code. There's a lot of hands. That's awesome.
---
我们问谁在用Claude代码，举手的很多。太棒了。
Thank you for joining us, Boris. It's very special
---
感谢您光临Boris，能请到您非常荣幸。嗯，
to have here. Um as a roomful of builders, I think
---
在座的都是开发者，我认为你们正在彻底改变构建这件事。
are changing building entirely. And so, I'm curious
---
所以，我很想探讨一下软件和编码的未来，
explore how about the future software, coding, and
---
以及我们应该把空闲时间都花在什么上面。
what we should spend all our free
---
我先简单补充点背景，让大家有点概念。
time on. but I'll give
---
除了创建Claude代码，
me tiny bit more background on that everyone has
---
Boris是一位真正的工程师中的工程师。
little context. So, beyond creating Claude
---
你的整个职业生涯写了大量东西，
code, Boris is much an engineer's engineer. You were writing
---
包括《TypeScript编程》这类教科书。
lot through your whole career, textbooks including programming in TypeScript. last
---
上次聊天时你说2026年之前几乎一行代码都没写过，
chatted hadn't written single line year, or at least far 2026,
---
或者说至少到2026年都没怎么写，这变化真不小。
which quite change. There's also known thing back middle school, wrote guide uh
---
还有个趣事：中学时你为TI-83 Plus计算器写过一篇
BASIC TI-83 Plus calculators.
---
BASIC指南。
And I just searched for it, it's actually still on the internet.
---
我刚刚搜了一下，它居然还挂在网上。这太尴尬了，
It's extremely embarrassing, so please don't search it. But [laughter] exists.
---
所以请大家别去搜。[笑声] 但它确实存在。
We will definitely be finding that. Um we're going to do I'm
---
我们肯定会把它挖出来的。嗯，我先问几个问题。
start with a few questions here. Maybe we'll little bit of history Claude code,
---
也许先聊聊Claude代码的历史，你是怎么开始的，
how you started and then have lot audience Q&A this one. thinking about your in back head,
---
然后留大量时间给观众问答。想着大家心里已经有疑问了，呃，
uh would love turn over all soon.
---
很快就把时间交给你们。
turn it over to you all soon. Yeah. Um and also
---
很快就把时间交给你们。是的。嗯，另外快速问一下，
real quick, so for people that use Claude code, do the CLI
---
用Claude代码的人，主要是用命令行界面吗？好，
mostly? Like okay, majority CLI?
---
大部分是命令行？
Okay. That's a lot. Majority desktop?
---
好的。很多啊。大部分是桌面端？
VS code or JetBrains IDE?
---
VS代码还是JetBrains集成开发环境？
Okay. Majority VS code or JetBrains IDE? That's actually
---
好的。大部分是VS代码或JetBrains IDE？
not a lot.
---
其实没有那么多。
Okay. That's actually not a lot. Other?
---
好的。其实没有那么多。其他呢？
I'm like iOS mostly these days. Yeah.
---
我最近主要用iOS。是的。
I'm like iOS mostly these days. Yeah. >> [laughter] Okay. Cool.
---
我最近主要用iOS。是的。>> [笑声] 好。酷。
>> Okay. Cool. Um
---
>> 好。酷。嗯，
yeah, so I started Claude code kind of accidentally in a lot ways.
---
其实我创建Claude代码在很多方面是偶然的。
Um I joined this team back late 2024.
---
嗯，我在2024年底加入了这支团队。
Um I joined this team back in
---
嗯，我在2024年底加入了这支团队。
late 2024. It was a sort of incubator within Anthropic called Labs.
---
它当时是Anthropic内部一个叫Labs的孵化器。
And uh the team kind of served its purpose.
---
而呃，这个团队也算是完成了使命。嗯，
Um we created Claude code, MCP, and desktop app. It was
---
我们创建了Claude代码、MCP和桌面应用。
a it just few us.
---
当时就我们几个人。
it was just a few of us. So, very much like innovation team.
---
当时就我们几个人。所以，很像一个创新团队。
We built the thing that we wanted to build,
---
我们最终建成了想建的东西，团队解散了——呃，
disbanded Uh now team's actually back together for round
---
现在团队又重组了，准备第二轮。你应该知道，
two. Mike Krieger, who's you know, chief product officer at
---
迈克·克雷格是Anthropic的首席产品官，
Anthropic and used be one of founders Instagram, so he's leading right now.
---
也是Instagram的联合创始人之一，目前由他主导。
that right now. Um so the kind of reason I started to work
---
目前由他主导。嗯，我开始从事编程工作的原因，
on coding is we felt like there
---
是我们觉得存在产品积压。
was this product overhang. And I'm guessing people here use word a lot. Uh but definitely lot in
---
我猜在座很多人经常用"积压"这个词——在实验室内部肯定也
within lab.
---
常提。
of within the lab. Uh there's this idea that model
---
实验室内部。有个概念是模型能完成所有事，
can do all stuff no product has yet captured. And
---
但还没有产品能实现这一点。2024年底，
in late 2024, when we were looking at coding, way did state art
---
当我们审视编程领域时，当时的最高水平是"提前输入"。
time was type ahead. It you open your IDE and press tab
---
你打开IDE，按Tab键，一次只能补全一行代码。
like complete one line a time. thing Sonnet 3.5 enabled
---
Sonnet 3.5首次实现了这一点，
for first But feeling could actually go lot further than that. almost ready next
---
但我们感觉还能走得更远——几乎准备好迈出下一步了。所以，
big step. So, don't have to ahead anymore, just agent write code.
---
不用再提前输入了，直接用智能体写代码就行。
the code. And so, I built it, and just really didn't work for first 6
---
写代码。于是我构建了它，但前六个月完全不行。效果很不好，
months. It was like not very good. barely usable. wrote from used maybe 10%
---
几乎没法用。我自己写，大概只有10%的代码用它。
of my code or something that. even after we released Claude initially, a hit.
---
即使我们最初发布了Claude，反响也并不热烈。
code initially, it was not a hit. There's lot of
---
最初反响并不热烈。很多人用过，
people that used but did have this exponential growth has today.
---
但并没有像今天这样的指数级增长。
growth that it has today. Um started with Opus 4 in May. And
---
今天这样的指数级增长。嗯，从五月的Opus 4开始。
I remember very clearly. That's like when the exponential
---
我记得非常清楚。那时开始呈指数级增长，
and then kind of inflected every model release. Uh 4.5, 4.6, now 4.7.
---
每次模型发布都拐点上扬。4.5、4.6，现在是4.7，
It just keeps inflecting.
---
一直在上扬。
But essentially, we were trying to build this thing that was like
---
但本质上，我们试图构建的产品处于产品市场契合前阶段，
pre-PMF, and knew it wouldn't have PMF for 6 months
---
而且知道未来六个月都不会达到产品市场契合，
because building the next model. And idea pretty much whole time.
---
因为还要构建下一个模型。这个想法几乎贯穿始终。
pretty much the whole time. And you know, for Anthropic in general, we've
---
几乎贯穿始终。你知道，对Anthropic整体而言，
always just been very focused.
---
我们一直非常专注。
We've cared about business and enterprise safety coding. That's kind of the way that we wanted
---
我们关心商业和企业安全编程。这就是我们想走的路。所以，
to build. And so, at some point knew build a product. We didn't know exactly what
---
在某个节点我们知道要构建一个产品，但不确定具体要什么。
wanted. So, this ended up being product bet.
---
于是这最终成了产品赌注。
being the product bet. It's an incredible story, especially that it was accident.
---
成了产品赌注。这是个不可思议的故事，尤其是它源于偶然。
that it was an accident. Um so, you've said on the record
---
源于偶然。嗯，你公开说过你认为编程问题已解决。
you think coding is solved. Uh if this one of three best
---
如果这是Anthropic最擅长的三件事之一，
from Anthropic, can tell us more about what mean by and might still
---
能否告诉我们更多含义，以及可能仍未解决的部分，
not be solved, or second-order problems come? All
---
或者会出现哪些二阶问题？好吧，
right. I ask another question for room. Who writes 100% their code hand?
---
我换个问题问大家：谁还在100%手写代码？
Who writes 100% of their code using a agent like Claude
---
谁在用像Claude Code这样的智能体写100%的代
code?
---
码？
Okay. Who's somewhere in between?
---
好。谁处于中间状态？
Okay. Who's like somewhere in between? So, 50% solved.
---
谁处于中间状态？所以，大概50%已解决。
Okay. So, like 50% solved. >> [laughter]
---
所以，大概50%已解决。>> [笑声]
>> I mean, for me it's like 100%. Like the Claude
---
>> 对我来说，基本是100%。Claude的代码库，
code base, um you know, it leaked, so people know.
---
嗯，你知道，它泄露过，所以人们知道。相当简单，
Uh pretty simple. It's just TypeScript and React. there's no big secret.
---
就是TypeScript和React。没什么大秘密。
it's React. Like there's no big secret. There's nothing really complicated. The
---
就是React。没什么大秘密。没有什么真正复杂的。
the reason we picked TypeScript and React is very on distribution
---
我们选择TypeScript和React的原因，
for model. So, when started, you know, building code base, model was
---
是模型的分布性很好。所以，当我们开始构建代码库时，
not as intelligent it today, so language framework mattered a lot. Nowadays,
---
模型没有今天这么智能，所以语言和框架很重要。如今，
can write whatever, pick up new languages, frameworks hasn't seen. But back
---
你什么都能写，能掌握没见过的新语言和框架。但那时，
then, wanted to use something pretty distribution.
---
我们想用分布性好的东西。
to use something pretty on distribution. Because of
---
用分布性好的东西。正因为如此，
that, I think fairly early we got the point where model just wrote 100%
---
我觉得很早我们就达到了模型能写100%代码的程度。
code. And for us, this happened sometime in October, November last year.
---
对我们来说，这发生在去年十月到十一月左右。
And so, for me today, you know, like the model writes 100% of my code. I
---
所以今天对我来说，模型写了我100%的代码。我自己写，
write somewhere, usually a few dozen PRs every day.
---
通常每天提交几十个拉取请求。
Uh there was a day last week I did like 150 in That that
---
上周有一天我做了150个——破了纪录。
record. just trying to kind of push see how far can get it.
---
我只是想试试看能推进到什么程度。
push to see how far I can get it. Um but yeah, it's like
---
试试能推进多少吧。嗯，但对我来说，这问题已经解决了。
for me just solved. this is not the case everywhere. There's very big
---
不过并非所有地方都这样。有些非常大的复杂代码库，
complicated code bases. kind of weird languages model's good at yet. and you know,
---
模型还不太擅长那些古怪的语言。而且，在座各位都知道，
as everyone here knows, getting there. Usually answer wait next model.
---
要达到那种程度，通常得等下一代模型。
Can you actually tell us about your personal setup? You walked through it the other day.
---
能跟我们聊聊你的个人工作配置吗？你那天简单提过，
It is pretty wild.
---
挺狂野的。
the other day. It is pretty wild.
---
那天提过，确实挺狂野。嗯，
Yeah. Um so, I shared my personal setup like 6 months ago or something on Twitter. And
---
大概六个月前我在推特上分享过我的个人配置。有意思的是，
it it's funny, actually didn't realize that would be surprising for anyone. That was just way coded.
---
我当时真没觉得这会让任何人惊讶。那就是我写代码的方式。
like the way that I coded. >> [laughter] And it's changed since then.
---
就像我平时写代码那样。 >> [笑声] 但之后又变了，
It's changed. Um
---
一直在变。嗯，
and so, now actually most of my work do from phone.
---
实际上现在我的大部分工作都是在手机上完成的。
my work I do from phone. Um and so, don't know if like you guys won't be
---
我的工作都在手机上做。嗯，不知道你们能不能看到这个，
able to see this, but have um the Claude app, open on left-hand side, there's
---
但左边开着Claude应用，有个小代码标签，
little code tab, just a bunch of sessions going.
---
里面有好几个会话在进行。
Um you probably can't see it.
---
嗯，你们可能看不清。
>> How many sessions?
---
>> 有多少个会话？
Uh usually have like maybe five to 10 sessions. and then the sessions a bunch
---
通常大概五到十个会话。然后每个会话里有一堆代理，
of agents, so I think currently probably few hundred going.
---
所以现在大概有好几百个在运行。
hundred agents going. Um usually
---
好几百个代理在跑。
every night I have like a few thousand that are doing kind of deeper
---
通常每天晚上我会有几千个在做更深层的工作。
work. There's ways to manage it.
---
有一些管理方法。
work. There's a few ways to manage it. One is that you ask Claude use bunch of sub-agents do
---
有一些管理方法。一个是让Claude用一堆子代理来处理
bunch of sub-agents to do work.
---
一堆子代理来做工作。实际上，
Actually, the thing that I've been finding
---
我发现自己用得越来越多的是循环。
myself using more and is loop. So, this \slash} loop, it's just
---
就是这个\\}循环，真是太酷了。
like coolest thing. It's
---
最简单却最有效。
simplest works. All it you have Claude use cron schedule a job for some
---
就是让Claude用cron定时任务在未来的某个时间点执
point in future, repeat job.
---
行，然后重复执行。
future, and it's a repeat job. And it can run every minute, 5
---
未来的某个时间点，并且是可重复的任务。它可以每分钟、
minutes, day, kind of however often you want to schedule it.
---
每五分钟、每天运行，你想怎么调度都行。
And at [snorts] this point, I have like dozens of
---
到了 [哼] 现在，我有好几十个循环在跑各种事情。
loops that are running for stuff. So, one that's babysitting my PRs,
---
有一个在盯着我的Pull Request，负责修复CI、
fixing CI, auto-rebasing. another keeps healthy.
---
自动变基。另一个在维护
have another one that keeps CI
---
另一个在维护CI的健康。
healthy. So, like if there's a flaky test or whatever, it'll go and
---
比如如果有不稳定的测试之类的问题，它就会去修复。嗯，
fix it. Um I grabs uh feedback from Twitter kind of clusters it
---
它还会从推特抓取反馈，每30分钟帮我分类整理一下。
for me every 30 minutes. just bunch these loops
---
任何时候都有一堆这样的循环在运行。
running at any time. sort feel are the future this point. If you haven't experimented
---
我觉得循环就是未来的方向。如果你还没试过，强烈推荐试试。
with highly recommend And we also launched routines, which is same
---
我们还推出了例程，本质一样但跑在服务器上。
thing but on server. even close your laptop, going.
---
就算你合上笔记本电脑，它也在跑。
keeps going. So, that's your personal setup. Tell us about what
---
它会一直运行。以上就是你的个人配置。跟我们说说，
you think teams will look like in
---
你认为未来的团队会是什么样？
the future. How do extrapolate from all work
---
你是如何从你做的这些工作中推断出，
you're doing to keep everyone on team moving forward, understanding context,
---
如何让团队中的每个人都保持前进、理解上下文，
or we need let go of a lot more agents make it work?
---
或者我们是不是需要放权给更多代理才能让它运转起来？
Um I think so you know, it's like hard to make predictions, but um I'm here I'll try some.
---
嗯，我觉得吧，做预测很难，但我在这儿，就试着说几个吧。
try to make some. I feel like the way that things are going
---
试着说几个。我感觉未来的大趋势是，
is generally there's be a lot more generalists than there today.
---
通才型人才会比现在多得多。
And today when we talk about generalists, I think largely we're talking people that are still engineers. So,
---
现在我们聊通才，基本上指的还是工程师。他们写代码，
they're writing code, but maybe kind of product say generalist, it's like a you know, they do iOS and
---
但可能算是产品通才，比如既做iOS也做Web服务器。
web server, for example. That's in engineering.
---
这都还在工程领域。
But I think the thing that we're going to start see a lot more of is generalists are cross-disciplinary.
---
但我认为，我们会开始越来越多地看到跨领域的通才。
generalists that are cross-disciplinary. So, this is engineers really
---
跨领域的通才。就是那些既擅长产品工程、
good at product engineering, but also great design. Or and data science engineering.
---
又擅长设计的工程师，或者既懂工程又懂数据科学的人。
Um I don't know. It's it's something that we're starting to see on our
---
嗯，我不太确定。这其实是我们团队正在出现的一种现象。
team. So, actually like a lot of people the Claude code team are generalists across disciplines.
---
实际上，Claude 代码团队里很多人都是跨学科的通才。
Everyone on our team codes. So, like engineering manager, product designers,
---
我们团队每个人都会写代码。比如工程经理、产品设计师、
data scientist, finance guy, user researcher, every single person writes code.
---
数据科学家、财务人员、用户研究员，每个人都在写代码。
team writes code. And so, you know, like they're specialist in
---
整个团队都写代码。所以，你看，他们虽然各有专长，
something, but now also everyone's just coding.
---
但现在每个人也都在写代码。
And you know, I'm seeing some nods, but I bet also it's actually not that surprising to people
---
我看到有人点头了，但我猜在座各位可能并不觉得这有多意外，
in this room cuz you're the same things.
---
因为你们的情况也差不多。
seeing the same things. Um [clears throat] I'll
---
大家都是类似的情况。嗯（清嗓子），
have one more favorite questions then we'll open up to audience. So,
---
我再问一个我最喜欢的问题，然后就开放给观众提问。
we talked a bit about what's changing with
---
我们刚才聊了编程正在发生的变化，
coding. I'm curious what you see in world of software or products.
---
我很好奇在软件或产品领域，你看到了什么趋势？
Um I think as we see AI making writing code 10 100x cheaper, what
---
嗯，我觉得随着 AI 让写代码的成本下降10倍甚至100
happens to the value products that are produced with software? Do
---
倍，用软件生产出来的产品价值会发生什么变化？
have a SAS apocalypse on our hands? How do you this plays out?
---
我们会不会面临一场SaaS末日？你觉得这会如何发展？
And again, you're going make another prediction.
---
再说一次，你要再做一个预测。
The SAS apocalypse question is my favorite then.
---
SaaS末日这个问题是我最喜欢的。
favorite question then. Um
---
最喜欢的提问。嗯。
I think there's two things that are going to happen and don't either of them is the thing people have been talking about.
---
我觉得会有两件事发生，而且都不是人们一直在讨论的那种。
I think one is Is anyone here an acquired listener? Like the podcast?
---
第一件事——在座有人听过《Acquired》这个播客吗？
Yeah, it's like the best podcast.
---
对，那是最好的播客。
Uh I actually got to do a unplugged with them other
---
嗯，我前几周还去录了一期《Unplugged》，
week and just felt meet my heroes cuz they're hosts are best.
---
感觉就像见到了我的偶像，因为那两位主持人是最棒的。
are the best. So, they have this idea of uh seven
---
他们是最棒的。他们有个“七种力量”的概念，
powers and is a like Hamilton. He kind wrote he
---
来自汉密尔顿写的那本关于商业模式的书。
book about modes in business. And I think what's going to happen because
---
我认为随着AI的发展，其中一些力量会变得更重要，
AI, some these get more important less important. so, for example, one
---
另一些则会弱化。比如，转换成本这种力量会减弱，
that gets switching costs you can just use model port from thing different thing.
---
因为你可以轻松地把模型从一个东西迁移到另一个东西。
from one thing to a different thing. Another that gets less
---
从一件事换到另一件事。另一种会弱化的是流程优势，
important is process power because for companies whose mode like
---
因为对于那些商业模式依赖工作流之类的公司，
workflows and things this, Claude getting really good at figuring out process. And
---
Claude已经非常擅长梳理流程了。特别是4.7版本，
especially with 4.7, it can just hill climb anything. So, if
---
它可以自动爬山优化任何目标。你只要给一个目标，
you give target tell iterate until it's done,
---
说“迭代直到完成”，它就会照做。
will do it. I think the first model that.
---
我认为这是第一个能做到这点的模型。
is the first model like that. So, I think these are going to get
---
是第一个这样的模型。所以我认为这些因素会变得不那么重要，
less important, but previous modes actually still matter. this network effects, uh
---
但之前的商业模式其实仍然有效。像网络效应、规模经济、
scale economies, cornered resources, things These not really changing with AI.
---
稀缺资源这些东西，并不会因为AI而改变。
I think the second thing is if you look at number of startups today or like maybe in
---
我认为第二件事是，看看今天或未来十年内的创业公司数量，
next know, past 10 years, that are just going to disrupt everything increase 10x.
---
那些能够颠覆一切的公司可能会增加10倍。
increase like 10x. Because right now you can be a tiny
---
增加10倍。因为现在你可以是一个很小的创业公司，
startup, could build thing that's as valuable large company and actually compete head-to-head
---
却能打造出和大公司一样有价值的产品，并且直接正面竞争。
because the has to evolve their business process, they have
---
因为大公司必须调整业务流程、改变工作方式、
way work, retrain everyone use technology, they're going face lot of internal resistance that.
---
重新培训所有人使用新技术，它们会面临大量内部阻力。
resistance to that. But you know, no one here has that problem.
---
但你们在座的人没有这种问题。
you know, no one here has that problem. If you're starting
---
你们都没有这种问题。如果你是从零开始，
fresh, then can kind of build with AI natively from the ground up.
---
你可以从一开始就以AI为核心来构建一切。
So, I don't know. think it's the best time to
---
所以，我不确定。但我觉得这是最好的创业时代，
build. It's be a startup. there's so much disruption coming.
---
也是创业的最好时机。将会有巨大的颠覆来临。
So, there is hope for us after all.
---
这么说来，我们还是有希望的。
So, there is hope for us after all. Thank you, Boris.
---
这么说来，我们还是有希望的。谢谢你，鲍里斯。
Um I would love to open up audience questions if anyone has anything they like ask.
---
嗯，我很乐意开放观众提问环节，如果有人想问问题的话。
would like to ask. Dan?
---
有人想问问题吗？丹？
I Yeah, I'm curious.
---
我，嗯，我很好奇。
Um you said that built uh 6 months before there
---
你说在产品市场匹配前六个月就搭建了产品，
was product market fit, but now
---
但现在模型已经足够好了，
given the models are good enough, how much do attribute success of Claude code
---
你觉得Claude Code的成功有多少归功于模型本身，
to model versus like decisions in field product?
---
又有多少归功于产品领域的决策？
field of product? Uh I think it's probably a mix.
---
产品领域？嗯，我觉得可能是两者相结合。
Uh I think it's probably a mix. Yeah, if you asked me maybe year ago,
---
嗯，我觉得可能是两者相结合。对，如果你一年前问我，
the ratio was something like 50/50.
---
比例大概是五五开。
Um maybe I don't know. If you asked me 6 months ago, the mix would be
---
嗯，我不知道。如果你六个月前问我，比例可能还是
50/50. >> What about in 2 years?
---
五五开。 >> 那两年后呢？
Oh, year I don't know, dude. We plan like we 1 week out.
---
哦，老兄，我不知道。我们只规划未来一周的事。
in like we plan 1 week out. >> months. Sometime the future.
---
我们只规划未来一周。 >> 几个月？未来的某个时候。
>> months. Sometime in the future. [laughter] And by way,
---
>> 几个月？未来的某个时候。[笑声] 顺便说一句，
I think reason it was 50/50 is
---
我认为之所以是五五开，嗯，你知道，
um you know, like did YC back
---
就像YC（创业孵化器）早期教的那样。
day. first hire at a company and bunch of startups.
---
作为一家公司的第一个员工，参与过很多初创公司。
And in startups like the thing that they drill into you and then
---
在初创公司里，他们一直灌输的理念，尤其是YC，
especially YC over is build something people love.
---
就是打造人们喜欢的东西。
And so, it doesn't matter what the product is, like model
---
所以，产品是什么、模型之类的都不重要。
and all this stuff. You still in end have to
---
你最终还是要打造一个人们喜欢的东西。
build a thing that people I think that's why matters we pay much attention little details
---
我觉得这就是为什么我们如此关注你日常使用时的小细节，
as you use day, it's really great experience.
---
这确实是一种很棒的体验。
I think as the model's gotten better, harness kind of gets less important.
---
我觉得随着模型变得更好，工具层的重要性会降低。
the harness kind of gets less
---
工具层的重要性会降低。
important. And I think like that we're thinking about right now
---
我认为我们现在思考的是如何改进工具层？
is how do we evolve harness? So, make loops more
---
比如让循环操作成为更核心的功能？
a first class thing? How it easier to run lot agents? Uh you
---
如何让运行多个智能体更简单？嗯，你知道，
know, beside sub agents one idea.
---
子智能体是个想法。
know, like sub agents is one idea. There's a bunch more stuff that we're cooking.
---
对，子智能体是一个想法。我们还在酝酿更多的东西。
But I think in a year, the model will be much
---
但我认为一年后，模型的对齐能力会好得多。
better aligned. And so, all safety mechanisms that we have today around uh
---
所以我们今天所有的安全机制，比如提示注入防护、
prompt injection and kind of static verification commands permission modes, human loop,
---
静态验证命令、权限模式、人工介入循环等等，
this stuff is just going to less important cuz do right thing.
---
都会变得不那么重要，因为模型会做正确的事。
do the right thing. Um So, yeah, that's my prediction.
---
会做正确的事。嗯，这就是我的预测。
You want to toss the box, Dan? >> [snorts]
---
你想扔一下盒子吗，丹？ >> [喷鼻声]
>> Great. Um To zoom to out a little bit
---
>> 太好了。嗯，如果从软件层面稍微拉远一点来看，
from software, I think Claude code did cultural change few months
---
我觉得 Claude 代码在几个月前带来了一种文化变革，
ago where it democratized like building software.
---
它让构建软件这件事变得大众化了。
You can see uh shop owners their own um software for themselves or even programming microcontrollers
---
你可以看到店铺老板为自己编写软件，甚至用编程控制单片机，
to control the light when someone opens door.
---
在有人开门时自动开关灯。
Um do you see in future um building software becoming a skill like
---
嗯，你认为未来构建软件会不会成为像“我会用 Micros
uh I know Microsoft Office? so, it's thing that
---
oft Office”这样的通用技能？
ev- everybody can not just people tech industry? Oh my god, yes.
---
变成每个人都能掌握的东西，而不仅仅是科技行业的人？
Yes. think going to be even more than that. don't
---
哦天哪，当然会。我觉得甚至还不止于此。
know. It's yeah, how send text message.
---
就像现在谁都会发短信一样。
I think um you know,
---
我觉得，嗯，你知道的，
like read a my two genres are essentially sci-fi and
---
我阅读的两大主题基本就是科幻和技术史。
tech history. This is what lot of.
---
这是我大量阅读的内容。
history. This is what I read a lot of. think in
---
技术史。这是我最常读的东西。在技术史中，
tech history, there's one thing which to me the clearest parallel for what's happening
---
有一个在我看来与当下正在发生的事情最为清晰的类比。
right now. And this 1400s, printing press Europe.
---
那就是15世纪欧洲的印刷术。
the printing press in Europe. And what happened was before essentially 10% of European population literate. They knew
---
欧洲的印刷术。在当时，大约只有10%的欧洲人口识字。
how to read and write.
---
他们懂得读写。
They were often employed by like kings lords that not literate.
---
这些人通常受雇于国王和不识字的领主。
and lords that were not literate. And their job was to you know,
---
以及那些不识字的领主。他们的工作就是读写，
read write this is something everyone knew how do.
---
而这是当时人尽皆知的事情。
>> [snorts] The printing press was invented, then there were two
---
>> [轻笑声] 印刷术被发明之后，又出现了两台印刷机。
more presses and in the 50 years
---
在第一部文学作品出版后的50年内，
after first literature published Europe than thousand before.
---
欧洲的文献数量比之前的一千年还要多。
And over the
---
而在同一时期，
same period, cost of literature, a book went down like 100x.
---
文献的成本——一本书的价格下降了大约100倍。然后，
then, you know, it took couple hundred years cuz learning to
---
你知道的，这又花了几百年时间，因为学习读写本身很难。
read and write is hard. You need
---
你需要建立教育体系、需要政府推动、
education systems government everyone can't be working on farms so on. But
---
不能让所有人都还在农场干活等等。但接下来的几个世纪里，
next few literacy globally up 70%. now we can all don't degree
---
全球识字率上升到了70%。现在我们所有人都能读写，
in reading writing how write.
---
不需要专门拿个读写学位。
Although still there are professional writers that thing do.
---
尽管仍然有专业的写作者在做这件事。
is a thing that you can do. So, I think the that's about to happen
---
这是每个人都能够做的事。所以，我认为同样的事情即将发生，
and it's going be much faster than 50 years software will fully democratized, anyone
---
而且会比50年快得多——软件将被彻底普及，任何人
can do. And you know, there's a lot of corollaries to this. So, for
---
都能做。而且，你知道的，这有很多推论。比如，
example, let's say you're writing accounting software.
---
假设你在编写会计软件。
The best person to write accounting software, I think maybe even
---
我认为，编写会计软件的最佳人选，甚至可能到今天为止，
today, is not an engineer, it's a really good
---
都不是工程师，而是一位真正优秀的会计师，
accountant because they know the domain well and coding easy part.
---
因为他们对领域非常熟悉，而编码反而是简单的部分。
really well and coding is the easy part. It's knowing domain that's hard And
---
非常熟悉，编码反而是简单的部分。真正难的是了解这个领域。
I think this just obviously future.
---
而我认为这显然就是未来。
So, uh one of the things Greg said
---
所以，嗯，Greg 说过的一点是，
was that you guys are living in
---
你们某种程度上已经生活在未来了，
future a little bit cuz get to
---
因为你们能够使用模型和智能体。
have access models and agents. Claude code an internal tool before released
---
Claude 代码在发布之前曾是一个内部工具。嗯，
it. Um is gap between where engineering rest world, month? Is it 3 months?
---
工程领域和外部世界之间的差距是一个月吗？还是三个月？
world, is that a month? Is it 3 months? 6
---
世界，是一个月吗？还是三个月？六个月？
And gap getting bigger or smaller over time?
---
而这个差距是在变大还是在变小？
Yeah, so internally, we use the same models everyone else does.
---
是的，实际上在内部，我们使用的是和外部所有人一样的模型。
Um for us,
---
嗯，对我们来说，
the dog fooding is really important. So, we
---
内部试用（dog fooding）非常重要。
use thing that here you know,
---
所以我们用这些东西，你知道的，
like a little bit of mythos to
---
比如先小范围试用一下 mythos，
try it and then lot Opus 4.7 food write most our code.
---
然后大量用 Opus 4.7 来编写我们大部分的代码。
of our code. Um I think on the model side, there isn't
---
我们的代码。嗯，我认为在模型层面，其实没有什么差距。
really a gap. you know, it's like pretty
---
你知道的，就像 mythos 一样，
much mythos and that will become some version descendant available at point to everyone.
---
它最终会以某个版本的后代形式在某个时间点向所有人开放。
available at some point to everyone. I think
---
在某个时间点向所有人开放。我认为在产品层面，
on the product side, there's probably a far larger gap.
---
差距可能要大得多。而这只是因为我们在改变我们所有的流程。
And that's just related us changing all
---
如果你和 Anthropic 的人聊天，
of our processes. Like if you talk
---
你会发现我们实际上什么都用 Claude。
people Anthropic, we use Claude for literally everything. Claudes
---
Claude 们整天都在对话——就像我在编码时，
are talking
---
我的内循环中，
day like as I'm coding, my in loop, they will communicate
---
它们会通过 Slack 和其他人的 Claude 交流，
over Slack other people's that also running kind figure out unknowns.
---
而那些 Claude 也在运行，去弄清楚一些未知的东西。
We have no more manually written code anywhere
---
我们公司现在没有任何地方再手写代码了。
at the company. All of SQL is by uh models. Everything
---
所有SQL都由模型生成。所有东西都是自动构建的。
just built So, I think actually place that we're ahead
---
所以我认为，实际上我们领先的地方并不是技术，
not technology cuz same available to us everyone here
---
因为同样的工具对所有人来说都是可用的，
because fundamentally, we are building a platform. And
---
核心在于我们正在构建一个平台。因此，
so, for it's really important developers can use thing using and dog
---
开发人员能够用上我们推出的所有东西，并且亲自试用，
food everything put out there.
---
这一点非常重要。
everything that we put out there. But I think there's actually a far bigger weed
---
我们推出的所有东西。但我认为，在组织结构和流程方面，
in kind of the organizational structure and process. And this is place
---
其实有一个更大的问题。而这就是一个地方，
where you know, hopefully can talk about it places like uh everyone learn from also evolve.
---
希望大家可以在这里讨论，让每个人都能学习并共同进步。
and also evolve. Yeah, I think that's one of the advantages startups have. It's
---
并共同进步。是的，我认为这就是初创公司的一个优势。
so much easier to start there.
---
从零开始要容易得多。
Yeah, um last time we talked,
---
是的，嗯，上次我们聊的时候，
I think you'd mentioned a little bit about
---
我记得你提到了一点关于多代理的内容，
multi-agent and it was very in code at the prior Sequoia event
---
而且在之前红杉的活动上，你说有一些事情正在推进中，
you that there were some things going down pipeline thing you're talking
---
是你正在考虑的东西。现在显然有了/slash批处理、
thinking about. Now obviously there's slash batch, loop, sub teams, teams. Can speak
---
循环、子团队、团队。你能谈谈是在模型层面还是框架层面，
to either model level harness how injecting priors objective function is changing kind
---
如何通过注入先验知识和目标函数，来改善这种委派任务、
of make this experience around delegating work, spinning up agents better? Cuz
---
启动代理的体验吗？因为很多事情是可以并行处理的。
so much parallelizable. You can do many faster feel like have overlay my
---
你可以做得更快，感觉我需要靠直觉来判断什么时候并行，
own intuition for when parallelize rather than understanding spin 10 something.
---
而不是理解如何启动10个代理来处理某件事。
can spin up 10 sub agents for something. Yeah, I mean on the product side,
---
可以为某件事启动10个子代理。是的，从产品角度来看，
it really just comes down to prompting.
---
这其实归结为提示工程。
That's how it is. And so, you know, we tweak prompts kind
---
就是这样。所以，你知道，我们调整提示词，
of help the model do stuff in parallel more.
---
帮助模型更并行地处理事情。
But also, honestly, as the model gets better, it
---
但说实话，随着模型变得更好，它自然会这样做。
just naturally does this.
---
所以像循环这样的功能，
And so, something like loop, I found actually 4.7, starts doing.
---
我发现实际上4.7版本就开始做到了。这真的很酷。嗯，
Uh which is really cool. It's uh you know, I'll tell
---
我会告诉它：“去拉取这个数据查询。”它就会说：“嘿，
"Go pull this data query." it's "Hey, noticed
---
注意到这个数据随时间变化。开始一个循环，
that changing over time. start a and give report
---
每30分钟给我一份报告。”我说：“太好了。
every 30 minutes." I'm "Great.
---
能发到我的Slack上吗？
Can send to me Slack?" then uses Slack MCP do that.
---
”然后它就用Slack MCP做到了。所以我认为，
So, think time, not on users figure out how hold tools better. if
---
未来用户不用再费心去想如何更好地使用工具了。如果是这样，
that's case, product design problem doing good job.
---
那就是产品设计的问题，要做好。
and like I'm not doing a good
---
而且好像我做得并不好。实际上，
job. It's really on the model to do
---
这要依靠模型本身更好地处理这些事，
this stuff better us kind of prompting it so naturally does this.
---
我们只需要给它合适的提示，它自然就能做到。
Um so, right
---
嗯，所以现在，
now it seems like a lot of us use um Claude or Codex these uh
---
我们很多人似乎都在用Claude或Codex这些云端工具
tools in the cloud to do our computing. But then, there are some
---
来进行计算。但也有人非常强烈主张让AI本地化。
very vocal advocates having your AI be local.
---
我可以想象，随着时间的推移，
And I could imagine over time as open
---
随着开源模型和其他技术的发展，
way models and other things catch up that this more possibility for
---
人们获得高质量编程辅助的可能性会更大。所以，
people get really high-quality coding assistance. So, I'm curious
---
我很好奇你未来几年的愿景是什么。
vision say next years something that. Do you see trajectory everyone still
---
你觉得整个趋势是大家仍然依赖集中式计算，
relying on centralized compute is pivot oh, we all just have local agents
---
还是会转向我们都有本地代理，不用担心被限速，
can rely they don't throttled benefits?
---
还能享受其他好处？
and other benefits? Yeah, I think it um don't know. There's maybe a
---
以及其他好处？是的，我觉得这个……不知道。
few ways to answer that. like kind of the most fundamental way that is doesn't matter.
---
可能有几种回答方式。最基本的一种是，这根本不重要。
answer that is it doesn't matter. Cuz I think now we're getting to the
---
回答是，这根本不重要。因为我认为现在我们正到达一个点，
point where model just able figure out. So, like by
---
模型能够自己搞定了。所以，再过几年，
a couple years from going be doing all code. It's starting agents. building environments.
---
模型将包揽所有代码工作。它会启动代理，构建环境。
going to be building the environments. And so, like if it decides actually I'll use local models do this,
---
它会自己去构建环境。所以，如果它决定用本地模型来做，
then you know, that's what it'll do.
---
那它就会这么做。
then you know, that's what it'll do. These I don't think these will be decisions that we are making as engineers anymore.
---
那它就会这么做。我认为这些将不再是工程师需要做的决策了。
We have time for a couple more questions, so I can toss this out.
---
我们还有时间再问几个问题，所以我可以抛出这个问题。
questions, so I can toss this out. Jamie.
---
问题，所以我可以抛出这个问题。杰米。
Nester. Thank you.
---
内斯特。谢谢。
It feels like one of the great uh decisions with Claude
---
感觉Claude Code一个很厉害的决定，
Code was making use fact that a lot developers' tools and workflows are local.
---
是利用了许多开发者的工具和工作流都是本地化这一事实。
But um that isn't necessarily always the case for
---
但对于一般的知识工作来说，情况不一定是这样，
sort of general knowledge work with,
---
很多人用的是云端工具。我很好奇，
you know, cloud tools. I'm curious how you're
---
你们是如何思考Co-work这个产品的，
thinking about this Co-work do give enough access to
---
它能否像Claude Code对开发者那样，
tools we use be powerful same way Claude Code is developers?
---
为我们使用的工具提供足够的访问权限，让它同样强大？
Code is for developers? Yeah, it's That's a really great question. Um
---
就像Code对开发者那样吗？是的，这是个非常好的问题。
I know when was uh at big
---
嗯，我知道当我在大公司的时候，
company, we took like 5 years moving all the environments
---
我们花了大概5年时间把所有环境迁移到远端。
to remote. It's just so much work, especially scale.
---
这工作量太大了，尤其是在大规模下。
especially at a big scale. Um but for
---
尤其是在大规模下。嗯，但对于知识工作来说，
knowledge work, largely, it's
---
它其实已经存在了，
there already with like Salesforce and Docs things that.
---
比如Salesforce和文档这类工具。
Docs and things like that. Um for
---
文档之类的。呃，对我们来说，
us, it's always just the simplest answer. It's MCP.
---
答案往往最简单——就是 MCP。
answer. It's just MCP.
---
答案就是 MCP。所以，
So, the same MCP connector that you have in
---
你在 Claude AI 里用的那个 MCP 连接器，
Claude AI, hook up like, know, Salesforce, Google
---
接上 Salesforce、Google 文档、
Docs, Calendar. Uh and then Co-work can use
---
日历什么的，然后 Co-work 就能用上它。
that. CLI it. Code everywhere
---
命令行操作，随处编码。
And for the systems that don't have MCPs,
---
对于那些没有 MCP 的系统，
like do you think that's where computer use is going to be a big opportunity?
---
你觉得这是不是意味着“计算机使用”会成为一个大机会？
Yeah, I think computer use is kind of a catchall.
---
没错，我觉得“计算机使用”算是一个万能方案。呃，
Um so, currently, for as far know, Anthropic like pretty ahead
---
目前据我所知，Anthropic 在这方面挺领先的。
on computers. And if you it through Co-work, it's quite
---
如果你通过 Co-work 来运行，效果相当不错。
good. able to much any piece software that have your computer.
---
基本上能操控你电脑上的任何软件。虽然现在速度还挺慢，
It's very slow, but does well now, especially with 4.7.
---
但表现已经很好，尤其是搭配 4.7 版本。
Um Yeah, but I think otherwise like MCP is kind of the answer.
---
嗯，但除此之外，我觉得 MCP 基本上就是答案了。你看，
It's And you know, all this stuff just doesn't matter that
---
这些杂七杂八的东西其实没那么重要。可以是 MCP、
much. It could be MCPs, APIs, some
---
API，或者某种程序化访问方式，
sort programmatic access cuz model care. to mo- To it's tokens.
---
因为模型只关心这个——它只认 Token。
it's just tokens. All right, we have time for one more question.
---
说到底就是 Token。好了，我们还能再问一个问题。
Sean, do you want to toss the Thank you.
---
Sean，你要不要抛个——谢谢。
Sean, do you want to toss the Thank you.
---
Sean，你要不要抛个——谢谢。呃，
Um you've kind of alluded this,
---
你刚才已经暗示过这一点，
but if like sometime ago saw probabil- product overhang and
---
但如果早些时候看到“概率性产品遗留问题”，
thought build a that
---
想着先搭个东西，
would then become more interesting once models got better, could just talk even
---
等模型变强之后它会变得更有意思——你能不能大概聊聊，
in vague terms about shape you'd today
---
你觉得从现在起半年到一年后，
think becomes much as get 6 months year?
---
什么样的东西会变得特别有价值？
better in 6 months to a year?
---
半年到一年后会变得更好？嗯，
Yeah, Claude design I think is really good example. It's uh it's pretty today.
---
Claude 设计就是个很好的例子。它现在已经挺不错了，
going get lot better.
---
但还会变得更好。
Um there's also a few things that we're cooking up for Claude Code uh are
---
呃，还有一些我们正在为 Claude Code 开发的东
going to be landing over the coming weeks. So, you'll see those.
---
西，未来几周就会上线。到时候你们就能看到了。
Um and then I think uh loop batch things like this around massively parallelizing agents,
---
然后，我觉得像这种循环批处理、大规模并行化智能体的事情，
that's going to get better.
---
也会变得越来越好。
And computer use is another good one.
---
“计算机使用”也是一个很好的例子。
And computer use is another good one. All right, Boris. Thank you so
---
“计算机使用”也是一个很好的例子。好了，Boris，
much for joining us. I think we'll be here a
---
非常感谢你来做客。我们还会在这儿待一会儿，
little longer if anyone has questions.
---
如果大家还有问题的话。